Daniel W. Biddle correspondence, September 1893-March 1895 C700
Indiana University Archives
Daniel W. Biddle correspondence
September 1893-March 1895
Indiana University Archives
Biddle, Daniel W., 1870-1954
C700
0.2 cubic feet 1 box
Daniel W. Biddle (1870-1954) was a student at Indiana University from September 1893 through Spring 1895. This collection consists of letters that Daniel W. Biddle wrote to his parents and his friend Janie Bartee during his attendance at Indiana University in Bloomington, Indiana from 1893-1895. The letters document Biddle's social and academic life at IU through details on his interactions with his roommates, classmates, and professors; his studies and laboratory work; and events on campus and in the Bloomington community, including an 1895 student protest supporting the removal of IU to Indianapolis.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Daniel W. Biddle was born on October 24, 1870 in Gilboa, Benton County, Indiana to parents Jerome H. and Lydia J. Biddle. Daniel Biddle attended Indiana University from September 1893 through Spring 1895. Upon departing IU, Biddle tested and received a teaching license, going on to teach and later farm in Benton County. He married Janie Bartee (1874-1925), with whom he frequently corresponded while at IU, in 1897. The couple had two sons. Janie passed away in 1925, and Daniel remarried in 1929 to Gertrude Besse (1880-1982).
In 1918, Biddle became secretary of the Remington Farmers Mutual Insurance Company, which his father founded. His subsequent career in insurance included serving as a charter member and director at several companies, including Indiana Farmers Mutual Insurance Company and Meridian Mutual Insurance Company. Biddle passed away on January 18, 1954.
Arrangement
The letters in this collection are arranged first by recipient and then chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of letters that Daniel W. Biddle wrote to his parents and to his friend Janie Bartee during his attendance at Indiana University in Bloomington, Indiana from 1893-1895. The letters document Biddle's social and academic life at IU through details on his interactions with his roommates, classmates, and professors; his studies, which encompassed geometry, algebra, Latin, rhetoric, literature, physics, geology, and psychology, and laboratory work; events on campus and in the Bloomington community, including a lecture by Jane Addams, the dedication of Kirkwood Hall, the 1895 Freshman-Sophomore "class scrap", and a student protest supporting the removal of IU to Indianapolis (the "removal question").
Separated Material
Biddle obituaries were transferred to the Daniel W. Biddle biographical reference file.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2018/036
Provenance
Donated to the University Archives by Janie K. Whaley, granddaughter of Daniel W. Biddle, in June 2018.
- Daniel W. Biddle correspondence, September 1893-March 1895
  - Letters written to parents (Box 1)
    - September-December 1893 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1894 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1894 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1895 (Box 1)
  - Letters written to Janie (Box 1)
    - September-December 1893 (Box 1)
    - January-February 1894 (Box 1)
    - March-September 1894 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1894 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1895 (Box 1)